<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Jacob found in a desert land: or, A recovery of the lost out of the loss (truly manifested;) wherein is discovered the work of the Lord in the creature, and how I travelled through the night of thick darkness, which hath over spread the whole world; and of my deliverance out of darkness into the true Light and truth: wherein is witness my heavenly call into the ministry of the everlasting truth. / Given forth for the everlasting name of the Lord sake, and for their sakes, who desire to know the truth, and how I came into the truth; that they that can believe it may receive some satisfaction, (out of which all despisers and unbelievers are excluded.) By a witness of the same in life and testimony, who am a sufferer for the pure seed sake, who am known to the sons of men by the name of George Whitehead; in contempt, by the generation of despisers, called, a Quaker. With a few words to them who have any desires left in them to know the truth, whether they be in forms of profession, or out of forms, that they may see themselves, and return from their evil. Also a voyce of the thunder of the Lord from his holy temple, uttered forth to the inhabitants of the earth, who are in the Army of the Dragon (whether rulers, teachers or people.).</title>
            <author>Whitehead, George, 1636?-1723.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 44 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96396</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1936</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E889_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R204021</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863752</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863752</idno>
            <idno type="VID">168407</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96396)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 168407)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 134:E889[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Jacob found in a desert land: or, A recovery of the lost out of the loss (truly manifested;) wherein is discovered the work of the Lord in the creature, and how I travelled through the night of thick darkness, which hath over spread the whole world; and of my deliverance out of darkness into the true Light and truth: wherein is witness my heavenly call into the ministry of the everlasting truth. / Given forth for the everlasting name of the Lord sake, and for their sakes, who desire to know the truth, and how I came into the truth; that they that can believe it may receive some satisfaction, (out of which all despisers and unbelievers are excluded.) By a witness of the same in life and testimony, who am a sufferer for the pure seed sake, who am known to the sons of men by the name of George Whitehead; in contempt, by the generation of despisers, called, a Quaker. With a few words to them who have any desires left in them to know the truth, whether they be in forms of profession, or out of forms, that they may see themselves, and return from their evil. Also a voyce of the thunder of the Lord from his holy temple, uttered forth to the inhabitants of the earth, who are in the Army of the Dragon (whether rulers, teachers or people.).</title>
                  <author>Whitehead, George, 1636?-1723.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Giles Calvert, and are to be sold at the Black Spread-Eagle at the west-end of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Septem: 26".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Doctrines --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:168407:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>IACOB found in a deſert Land: OR, A RECOVERY Of the Loſt out of the Loſs (truly manifeſted;)</p>
            <p>Wherein is diſcovered the work of the Lord in the Creature, and how I travelled through the night of thick darkneſs, which hath over ſpread the whole world; and of my deliverance out of darkneſs into the true Light and Truth: Wherein is witneſs my heavenly Call in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Miniſtry of the everlaſting Truth.</p>
            <p>Given forth for the everlaſting Name of the Lord ſake, and for their ſakes, who deſire to know the Truth, and how I came into the Truth; that they that can believe it may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive ſome ſatisfaction, (out of which all deſpiſers and unbelievers are excluded.)</p>
            <p>By a witneſs of the ſame in Life and Teſtimony, who am a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferer for the pure Seed ſake, who am known to the ſons of men by the name of <hi>George Whitehead;</hi> in contempt, by the generation of deſpiſers, called, a QUAKER.</p>
            <p>With a few words to them who have any deſires left in them to know the Truth, whether they be in forms of profeſſion, or out of forms, that they may ſee themſelves, and return from their evil.</p>
            <p>Alſo a Voyce of the Thunder of the Lord from his holy Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, uttered forth to the Inhabitants of the Earth, who are in the Army of the Dragon (whether Rulers, Teachers or People.)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> and are to be ſold at the <hi>Black Spread-Eagle</hi> at the Weſt-End of <hi>Pauls,</hi> 1656.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:168407:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:168407:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>IACOB found in a deſert Land:</head>
            <argument>
               <p>Or, a Recovery of the Loſt out of the Loſs,
<note place="margin">Deut. 32.10, 11, 12.</note> (truly manifeſted;) wherein is diſcovered the work of the Lord in the Creature, and how I travelled through the night of thick darkneſs, which hath over ſpread the whole world; and of my deliverance out of darkneſs into the true Light and Truth, wherein is witneſſed my heavenly Call into the Miniſtry of the everlaſting Truth.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Ehold the wonderous work of the Lord God, what he hath done for me according to his own purpoſe, through his eternal love and free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace to me ward, in bringing his Seed to Immortality, and my ſoul from under the powers of death, hell and the grave, and reſtoring the Creature into the Covenant of his ſeed, and bringing it from under the bondage of corruption; which for ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral years together I was under, and ſubject to vanity, and my heart was led aſtray from the living God, and I lived without the fear of God, according to the courſe of the world, as the Children of diſobedience do, in whom the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:168407:3"/>Prince of the Air rules, among whom I was a ſtranger to the Life of God, and under the wrath of God, a Child of diſobedience, who knew not whither I went, for I was a Child of darkneſs, and could not comprehend the Light, nor follow the Light, though in darkneſs it ſhined, and did often reprove me for ſin and diſobedience, and condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me for having followſhip with the unfruitful works of darkneſs; yet the Creature being over-ruled and ſubject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to vanity, by the power of the Serpent, and the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and deſires led away from the Light of Chriſt, with him who led into wickedneſs, and there was no power ſought truly after, nor received, whereby to reſiſt the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed one; but ſtill he prevailed againſt me while I was in the corrupt nature, where the Curſe had power: and I was brought up, according to the manner of the world, in the traditions and rudiments of the world partly, in natural learning, and to that for a time I applied my mind, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to my parents and kinreds deſire; ſo that for a time I grew and increaſed in that learning, though many vain traditions I learned, and in vain books, and fooliſh clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and verſes, as others did, I learned, and did pleaſe my Tutors; and in that learning exceeded many others who learned with me, and got the praiſe and eſtimation of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny people of the world, for that natural knowledge I grew into through learning; whereby for a time the fleſh did glory, and pride got up, and deceit over-ruled; and that was nouriſhed in me which was for death and deſtruction, and oftentimes when I was among other Children, who minded ſporting, and gaming, and playing, who would have enticed me to the ſame, and ſometimes did fall into playing with them, yet oftentimes I was troubled in mind, and I was not ſatisfied, for often I was reproved by the true Light in me, which I then knew not, and thereby I was reſtrained ſomtime from conforming with other Children in their ludeneſs, for which I became ſometime a reproach and an object of hatred to ſome of them: and I was then made to believe, that God would bring me to judgment for the wickedneſs and vanity I had been in, and ſometime
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:168407:3"/>I was ſmitten with fear and terror, when I was but a few years of age, when my wickedneſs was laid before me, and brought into my remembrance, by that Light, which I knew not, which condemned for ſin, unto which Light my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience alſo did bear witneſs, and my thoughts did accuſe me when I thought of what I had done in unrighteouſneſs: But when I forgat reproof, and hearkened to the wicked, who did alwayes ſtrive to make me enter into their wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, then I ſuddenly was led into vanities, and practiſed vain mirth and ſportings, and ſo was one with them, who made merry over the Witneſs of God, when his grace was turned into wantonneſs: But as for many groſs and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon pollutions of the world, which many others was and are guilty of, I was kept from acting in, and did ſtrive to keep out of, ſo that then I was ſcoffed at by ſome of the heathen, who lived in drunkenneſs, and exceſs, and great prophaneſs, when I could not joyn with them in their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of riot; but the ſame ground of rebellion was in me then, though not ſo far got out into the actions, and often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times from my childhood I was afflicted with ſickneſs, and the hand of the Lord was upon me, whereby I was plagued and ſmitten inwardly, and ſaw then that it was what I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved for the ſin that I had been acted in, and I deſired of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten that I might come to true Repentance for my ſin, and have endeavoured much to find it, yea, with tears, but could not, while my heart was led away to obey the will of the Devil, and ſo the deſires in me, which was after Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance and amendment of Life, they were often quench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed through the deceitfulneſs of ſin and the ſubtilty of my ſouls enemy, and thus was the Creature and the ſoul held under the power of darkneſs: And near about the the age of fourteen years I was put to teaching of Chidren in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural learning, and taught Children till after I knew the Truth, knowing it to be ſerviceable in its place for Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, as there was a neceſſity for it, ſo as that Children be brought up in good nurture, and in the fear of the Lord, which in his fear, when I came into the Truth, I did ſtrive to bring thoſe Children up in whom I taught, and with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:168407:4"/>then I did labour in that calling till I was called from it.</p>
            <p>And in the time when I was led away captive to fulfil the will of the wicked one, I went much after the worlds Teachers, and heard them, and had got a part in their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, and ſpended many times in hearing them day after day, till I was often weary with following and hearing them teach their own traditions, and much what they had gotten out of other mens writings, and added their carnal Inventions to the Saints words, and raiſed their Uſes, and Applications, and Doctrines, and Arguments, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, and Motives, as he did, whom for ſeveral times I uſually heard in the Steeple-houſe at <hi>Orton</hi> in <hi>Weſtmerland,</hi> who had deceived me and others under his Miniſtry, though he be of great eſtimation in the world, and other Prieſts, in the ſame nature with him, I heard ſeveral times: But ſomething in me was not ſatisfied with their Miniſtry, for I was alwayes learning there, and could not know the Truth, as many others under their Miniſtry are; and often while I was in the hearing of ſome of the worlds Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, my ſpirit was troubled, and when they gave people ſome of <hi>Davids</hi> Conditions to ſing, I could not ſometime joyn with them in ſinging, knowing I was ſhort of what they ſung in meeter concerning <hi>David,</hi> what he paſſed thorow, and how it was with him, when he was in ſorrow, and affliction, and joy, and in his deliverance from cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, which the Prieſts cauſed people to ſing, who both themſelves and their hearers are ſhort of, when in their ſinging they told God, it was ſo with them as it was with <hi>David,</hi> which often I durſt not, leaſt I ſhould have told God lies: And when I grew ſomething weary with thoſe Prieſts, and that profeſſion which I had gotten under their Miniſtry did wax old, then I began to ſee them to be groſs and wicked in their practiſes and lives, and I ſaw that the Scriptures witneſſed againſt them in many things they pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed, who themſelves ſpake againſt pride and covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and yet lived in them, as their practiſes and lives made and makes them manifeſt,</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:168407:4"/>
            <p> And then I went to hear ſome, who were ſeparated from them, who was gotten into higher forms than the Prieſts, and were got above the traditions and carnal Ordinances which the Prieſts do practiſe, and had a more true form of words than they, and yet it was but a little time that I fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed ſuch, for my ſoul was not ſatisfied there, and that of God in me was then in priſon, and not miniſtred unto by them, who were in their notional knowlede, above the Light and Life of Chriſt, and what they miniſtred to was but death, and the carnal mind by that miniſtry was fed, and that ſpoak and got the Saints words to ſpeak off, which had no right to them, and ſtill the Witneſs of God in my Conſcience purſued me, that in my mind I could not be quiet, and it often miniſtred condemnation to that nature in me, which they, who did run before they were ſent, did promiſe life and ſpeak peace unto, but here I had no peace, and thus in the unſtable mind I was toſſed too and fro with windy doctrines, which for a time was pleaſant to that mind which fed in them; but that pleaſure did wither, and they were as a tinkling Cimbal, or ſounding Braſs, which paſſed away, and that profeſſion which in the forms I had gotten did wax old.</p>
            <p>And when I was near about the age of ſixteen years, being in the year, as accounted, 1652, it pleaſed the Lord God to ſend ſome of his Meſſengers, called Quakers, through his own free Love to me wards, which in me was and is witneſſed, and received, by his own Seed, whom he hath gathered unto himſelf (in the North Country) where it was ſcattered,
<note place="margin">Jer. 23.8.</note> which is reproached by the world and called Quakers? But when I firſt went to hear theſe Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers of the Lord, being then led to hear them by a principle of God which I knew not then, but through them the Word of the Lord was miniſtred unto me, and the Witneſs of God in me did witneſs and anſwer to the ſame; which I did really believe, and my underſtanding was opened by the word of power, which through them was miniſtred, and I then ſaw that they were Witneſſes of the pure Truth of God, and ſaw that the Scriptures did
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:168407:5"/>witneſs for them, and for the Truth which they held forth and miniſtred, which long before I had ſought after, but could not find it, while I was led from the Light of Chriſt in me, by blind Guides and Hirelings, who had made a prey upon me, ſo that what the Meſſengers of Chriſt did miniſter was effectual in me, whereby I was turned from darkneſs to light, and this I received as the Word of the Lord,
<note place="margin">Rom. 10.8</note> and not as the word of man, for it was the Word of Faith, and it was nigh me, even in my heart, which in the love of Chriſt, wherein it was miniſtred, I received, and it through Love did work in me and was effectual, for by it the vails was rent, and at the appearance thereof light was divided from darkneſs in me, and then I knew where my Guide and Teacher was, which comprehended darkneſs; by which Light my mind was informed, and I brought to wait on the teaching of God within, which in the light I received, and through faith was ſubject to, and here I ſaw the war which I had to paſs through, and the ſtrength of the Serpent and his wiſdom, wherein I had been acted and ſeeding upon the Tree of Knowledge, where I was ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from the Life of God, and had no right to the Tree of Life, while I fed there; but when the vails was rent, and I ſaw the ſtrength of the Enemy of my ſoul, then I ſaw the Judgment of God upon the Prince of the World, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thoſe imaginations, and that wiſeom, wherein I had been lead from the ſimplicity and light of the Goſpel, to obey the Serpent, and to hearken to the voyce of ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers; but the Seed of God took root, and was treaſured up in me, and in the power of the Lord it aroſe in me, and wrought effectually, and here I received the teaching of God, and heard his voyce, and by his power the earth was ſhaken, and the foundation of that wiſdom wherein I had been, and to that I became a fool, that I might be wiſe in the living Knowledge of God, whoſe thunders in heaven and voyces which did run through the earth I heard, and ſaw famine and barrenneſs in the earth as a barren wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and in ſimplicity I was made willing to wait upon God, and to endure the Croſs of Chriſt, though for a time
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:168407:5"/>and times the enmity of the wicked one was ſtrong againſt me within and without, ſeeking to devour that Seed which through the Word of the Lord was begotten in me;
<note place="margin">Iſa. 57.15. and 66.9.</note> but the Power of the Lord waxed great in me, whereby I was brought low into the fear of the Lord, and made often to tremble at his Word, which Power grew plentiful in me, through the Faith of the Son of God, which waxed ſtrong and plentiful in me and thus by the faith of the operation of God, the Lord carried me on in obedience to him from faith to faith, and the myſteries of God and his Kingdom was revealed in me, who brought me out of darkneſs through the wilderneſs, where the man-child was preſerved for a time, and times, and half a time, from the wrath of the Dragon, who would have ſlain the man-child:
<note place="margin">Iſa. 9.6.</note> But now is he ariſen in his power and zeal, and the Prince of the world is caſt out, and he is born, which is the everlaſting Counſellor, the prince of Peace, who hath ſent war, and the fire, and the ſword into the earth, but hath accompliſhed the war, and eſtabliſhed peace in the earth, and with his glory fils the earth, and hath brought back the captivity of his Seed, and manifeſted his good will towards me,
<note place="margin">Gal. 1.15, 16.</note> in whom it hath pleaſed the Father to reveal him, who hath made manifeſt his eternal love in me, and wrought deliverance for my ſoul, and hath brought ſalvation and plenteous redemption to me,
<note place="margin">Luke 4.18.</note> whereby the captive out of the houſe of bondage is delivered, and hell is conquered,
<note place="margin">Heb. 12.27 28.</note> and death and the grave overcome, and that which was ſhaken remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and the Kingdom that cannot be removed given me, and the Creature with the Seed of God is reſtored into the everlaſting Covenant of God, and he is ſlain who had the power of death, who did ſubject the Creature unto vanity in hope.</p>
            <p>And this hath the Lord done for me, whom he hath known and foreſeen, for his Seed ſake in me,
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.29.</note> and for the love of his own Son, who did enlighten me, and conformed me to the Image of his own Son, who is the firſt-born, and my foundation, and a Rock of defence to me and to all, who believe in him, and receive his teſtimony, who can ſet
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:168407:6"/>to my ſeal that God is true,
<note place="margin">Joh. 3.3</note> whoſe Righteouſneſs hath looked down from Heaven, and Mercy and Peace hath he eſtabliſhed in the Earth; and now is ſuch called the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God,
<note place="margin">Rom. 9.25.</note> who was not his people, and that which was barren brings forth and rejoyceth, and this I witneſs, as one who have obtained mercy through the Redemption of Chriſt Jeſus,
<note place="margin">Iſal, 54.1.</note> through whom my Lot is fallen unto me in a pleaſant place: and now hath the Lord brought me into the fruitful hill of <hi>Sion,</hi> where his praiſe is exalted, in the Immortality of his own Son, who is King of Kings, and Lord of Lords,
<note place="margin">Mat. 19.29 Mark 10.29.30.</note> who liveth and raigneth for ever and ever, whoſe teſtimony I am made to witneſs; for which cauſe the Lord hath called me from my native Country, and from my Fathers houſe, and from outward riches and the honour of the world, and hath redeemed me out of kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds, tongues and people, and to publiſh his Name and Power among the Inhabitants of the earth, and to witneſs his ſalvation to the ends of the earth and to miniſter good things to the Seed which God is gathering from the ends of the earth, and to call people out of darkneſs, and from among deceivers, who have long made a prey upon them, and to turn them to the true Light,
<note place="margin">John 1.9,</note> which lighteth every man that cometh into the world, that through the Light they may believe, and be delivered out of deceit, and out of the mouths of dumb Shepheards, who eat up the ſin of the people, and who have made and makes merchandize of the people through covetouſneſs with feigned words;
<note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.</note> and to my teſtimony thouſands will ſeal and witneſs againſt the changeable Prieſts, and Hirelings, and Diviners, and Deceivers, that are in the world, and to judge the Whore, who hath deceived the Nations with her Inchantments, and to torment the Beaſt, and plague the falſe Prophet, whoſe judgment, and torment, and miſery is now begun, and will never have end, for the word of the Lord is made manifeſt, and his teſtimony is given, which I witneſs, whom God hath ſet to root out, and to pull down, and to deſtroy, and to throw down, to build, and to plant; and this is the Covenant of the Lord God unto me,
<note place="margin">Jer. 1.10.</note> which is to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:168407:6"/>them that turn from iniquity in <hi>Jacob,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſai. 59.21:</note> his Spirit which is upon me, and his word which he hath put in my mouth,
<note place="margin">Heb. 11.25</note> ſhall not depart from me from henceforth and for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more;
<note place="margin">Rev. 13.7.</note> though for the everlaſting teſtimony of God I ſuffer affliction with the people of God, and do endure the envy of the Beaſt for a time, who hath power for a time to overcome the Saints, yet through theſe ſufferings,
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 6.4, 5.</note> and impriſonments, and beatings, and abuſings, and cruel mockings, and deſpiteful uſage, which I endure in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, I am approved of by God in the work of his Miniſtry, for which cauſe, and for whoſe ſake, I am not onely wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to ſuffer affliction, but alſo to lay down my life, and the ſufferings of this preſent time is not worthy to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to the glory that is revealed in me, and through all theſe ſufferings I am made more than a Conqueror.</p>
            <p>Let all the Saints and Righteous ones rejoyce with me for evermore, and witneſs forth the praiſe and glory of our God, for his Kingdom, and Glory, and Dominion is come and Judgement ſits, and the great Whore is judged, and <hi>Babylon</hi> is come in remembrance before the Lord, who is confounding it, and giving her double of his fury forher abominations, of which all Nations have drunk, who ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther themſelves together againſt the Lamb and his Tribe, but he ſhall overcome them, for they know not the thoughts of the Lord, neither underſtand they his Counſel, for he ſhall gather them as the ſheaves into the floor, therefore ariſe. O Daughter of <hi>Zion,</hi> and threſh with thy new ſharp threſhing Inſtrument having teeth, for the Lord is making thine horn iron, and thy hoof braſs, and thou ſhalt beat in pieces many people, and tread down, and raign over the Nations, O Remnant of <hi>Jacob,</hi> who art de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed of the people, and hated of the ſeed of the wicked, plague the Earth, and threſh the falſe Prophet, and the Beaſt; for wo is unto them and all their off-ſpring, and wo unto the Inhabitants of the Earth, and of the Sea, for the Devil is caſt out unto them, and hath great wrath, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he knoweth his time is but ſhort; but rejoyce ye hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, and ye that dwell therein, over <hi>Myſtery Babylon,</hi> and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:168407:7"/>over the great Whore, for her judgment is begun, and the ſmoak of her torment ſhall aſcend up for ever and ever, Allelujah, and Glory to the moſt high for evermore.</p>
            <p>Thus was I moved by the Spirit of the living God to give forth, for the ſimple ones ſake, who are groping in the dark, whether in forms, or out of forms, who are not ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but yet have ſome deſires to know the Truth as it is in Chriſt Jeſus, who <hi>is the Way the Truth and the Life, which whoſoever follows ſhall not abide in darkneſs, but ſhall have the Light of Life;</hi> and there ſhall be no occaſion of ſtumbling, but by the Builders, and by ſuch as live in the wiſdom of the fleſh, and are wiſe in their own eyes, he is rejected, and to them become a Rock of offence, but to them that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in him, and follow him, he is a Rock of defence, and become the head of the Corner, the chief Corner-ſtone, and true foundation, and the Author of ſalvation.</p>
            <p>From me, whoſe deſire is for the good of ſouls, who would not the death of finners, but rather that they ſhould turn from their wickedneſs and obtain remiſſion of ſins; I am a ſufferer for the everlaſting Truth ſake, and for the good Seed ſake, by which I am witneſſed in my ſuffering, and for whoſe ſake it is effectual, and through my ſuffering the Truth of God is exalted,
<note place="margin">Rev. 2.10.</note> though it be contrary to the envy of the wicked one who caſt me into priſon; where I have been a ſufferer above a year, and have endured exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing much abuſe by Tyrants, and am not convinced of the breach of any known Law that ever could be laid to my charge, either at my Impriſonment or ſince: But the Lord is my Refuge, though I have no helper in the earth.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>The ninth day of the ſixt moneth, in the year, as ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted, 1656.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>The earthly name by which the world knows me is</hi> George Whitehead, (<hi>Priſoner of the Lord in</hi> Edmonds-Bury <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Goale in the County of</hi> Suffolk) <hi>who a name hath writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in heaven, which none knows but they that are redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the earth.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:168407:7"/>
            <head>A few words to them who have any deſires left in them to know the Truth, whether they be in forms of profeſsion, or out of forms, that they may ſee them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and return from their evil.</head>
            <p>TO you that live without the knowledge of the true God, and know not his power, neither are come into the life of the Saints in light, you who are groping in the dark, you go you know not whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and have long been ſeeking, and have not found ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction nor reſt to your ſouls, for whoſe good my deſire is; my meſſage I declared unto you, That <hi>God is light,
<note place="margin">John 1.5.</note> and in him is no darkneſs;</hi> and he hath ſent his Son into the world a light to bring out of darkneſs,
<note place="margin">Iohn 1.9.</note> and out of the deeds of darkneſs, he is the true light, wherewith he lighteth eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man that cometh into the world, and he is the power of God to ſalvation to them that follow him, and believe in him: therefore every one of you return to the true Light, and with it ſearch your ſelves, and try your wayes, for now is the Lord viſiting you, and now is he calling you out of darkneſs, and to caſt off the unfruitful works of darkneſs, and to break off your iniquities by true repentance, that therein you may not periſh but have life in the true Light; and this is the love of God to the world, which they that refuſe, and chuſe to go on in ſtubbornneſs and enmity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the light, which reproves them for their wickedneſs, it is their condemnation,
<note place="margin">Iohn 3.19.</note> for they hate the light becauſe their deeds are evill, and they will not bring their deeds to the light, leaſt it ſhould reprove them; and theſe want
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:168407:8"/>power to overcome ſin, and to ſlay the enmity, and they go on in darkneſs they know not whither, and they are in unbelief, &amp; there they are excluded from the Life of God, let them profeſs what they will of the Prophets, or of Chriſt, or his Saints, or their words; &amp; here the light hath no fellowſhip with darkneſs, nor with them who hate it, and love darkneſs better than light, and ſuch find no power o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver their wils, nor over their luſts, nor vile affections, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they deny him who is the Power of God; and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong ſuch the powers of darkneſs have dominion, and deſtruction is in their wayes, and the curſe and wrath of God abides upon them,
<note place="margin">John 3.36. Iſai. 42.6. and 49 6.</note> who hate the Light, they deſpiſe the Covenant of God which Chriſt the Light is given for, and ſuch are ſeduced and kept from the knowledge of the pure God: and theſe are without God in the world, which lives in wickedneſs: therefore all you, in whom there is any deſires remaining after the living God, and to know his power, return to the Light of Chriſt within you, and it will let you ſee,
<note place="margin">Eph. 4.17.</note> how you have ſpent your time, and where your hearts are, and how you have been toſſed to and fro in the dark, and your minds have been exerciſed in vanity, and by the ſubtilty of the Serpent, for his kindom of ſin you have been reaſoning, and could not find a way out of it,
<note place="margin">Rom. 8, 20.</note> and yet the Serpent hath put you in hope of mercy and forgiveneſs of ſins, though you go on in ſin in your life time, and do not find the nature of ſin ſubdued; this is he who beguiled <hi>Eve,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen, 3.4.</note> and ſaid, ye ſhall not ſurely die (though they eat of that which God had forbidden) but take heed how you hearken to his voyce, either within you, or in his Meſſengers without you, leaſt you be beguiled with his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilty, and left to the eternal wrath of God, in the guilt of your ſins, which guilt remains ſo long as ſin remains, and ſo here the Covenant of God you reject, and puts of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, and deſpiſes the day of healing; and here is preſumption, and ſelf-willedneſs, and conceitedneſs, and pride, and covetouſneſs, and perverſeneſs lived in, and here the grace of God is turned into wantonneſs,
<note place="margin">Jude 4.</note> and the luſt of the fleſh rules, and the members are ſubject to vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:168407:8"/>and the fear of God you are out of,
<note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.13.</note> and you going on in that nature, contrary to the Light, you wax worſe and worſe; and here the will of the Devil you fulfil, who is the Author of ſin, and ſo you deny Chriſt and his coming, who is made manifeſt to deſtroy the works of the Devil, and to take away the ſins of the world;
<note place="margin">1 John 3.5.8.</note> though you may profeſs Chriſt and his doctrine in words, yet your profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on will not hide you,
<note place="margin">John 1.29. 1 Pet. 2.9. 1 Tim. 6.3, 4, 5.</note> nor ſave you from his judgment and wrath which upon the ungodly muſt come; and you that apply your minds to diſputings and vain janglings about the Saints conditions, and what they practiſed, who you your ſelves are out of the Saints life, and can get no further than the form of godlineſs in words, and many of you ſcarce to the true form; you are in the many opinions, and ſects, and vain contendings, and with that ſpirit you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend which is out of the truth, and which is ignorant of the Life that gave forth the Scriptures, and here there are ſo many opinions and differences, that poor ignorant peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple knows not what way to chuſe, nor which is the truth; you are the unſtable minded, and you are in your own wils, which are contrary to the Light, and to the Saints conditions you are ſtrangers, and have nothing to do to talk or diſpute about the Saints,
<note place="margin">2 Pet. 1, 21.</note> and what they ſpoak as they were moved by the Spirit of Truth, and were in the Life of what they ſpoak, and knew him,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 14.33.</note> who is not the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of confuſion, and contention, nor ſtrife, but of peace, and they knew him to be the life and ſubſtance of all figures and types; and he hath aboliſhed in the fleſh,
<note place="margin">Eph. 2.15.</note> the Law con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in Ordinances, for to make in himſelf of twain one new man ſo making peace:
<note place="margin">Gal. 4.</note> but you that are turned from the light, and do live in your carnal imaginations, and conceivings, and rudiments, and beggerly elements of the world,
<note place="margin">Col. 2.20.</note> and carnally have been imagining to find or meet with Chriſt there, you are ſtrangers to the knowledge of God, and his Law within you, you diſobey and reject, ſo all your profeſſion, and all your duties, and will-worſhips, the Lords denies, and the light condemns them, and there you find no peace, for that light which condemns you, for
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:168407:9"/>your erring from the pure Law of God, it purſues you, and brings trouble upon you, and ſhews you darkneſs, and that you are ſhort in life of what you profeſs in words, and though you profeſs that Chriſt died for you, and that he hath born your iniquities, yet the Light will let you ſee, that you are not dead with Chriſt, as he was to the fleſh, the world and the devil, who entered not into temptation, and ſo you are alive in your ſins, and the bloud of Chriſt you trample in,
<note place="margin">Phil. 3.10.</note> and are enemies to his croſs, whoſe minds are earthly, and ſo your iniquities are upon your ſelves, and Chriſt is not guilty of them, nor of your bloud; but his death and ſuffering witneſſeth againſt you: and whoſe ſins Chriſt hath nailed to his croſs, they are crucified and blotted out, and neither the action nor the guilt of ſin re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains in ſuch, and whoſe ſins Chriſt takes upon him, and nails to his Croſs,
<note place="margin">Rom. 6.2. 1 Pet. 2.24.</note> it is, that they being dead unto ſin may live no longer therein, and it is ſuch that have right in the death of Chriſt, and ſuffer with him, and take up the Croſs, and deny themſelves, and follow him: But thou, who in words profeſſes Chriſt and his death, for thee, examine thy ſelf, and ſee how far thou obeys his doctrine, and takes up the Croſs: He commanded to love thy neighbour as thy ſelf;
<note place="margin">Math. 5.</note> and to his he ſaid, do good to them that hate you, and he ſaid, ſwear not at all, and in all your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munications, let your yea be yea, and your nay be nay: ſee how far thou canſt own this in life and practiſes; and if a man ſmite thee on the one cheek, turn to him the other al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo: and if a man ſue thee at Law and take away thy coat, let him have thy cloak alſo: and he that taketh away thy goods,
<note place="margin">Luke 6.30.</note> ask them not again; and be ye perfect, as your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther which is in heaven is perfect. But there is much rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonings againſt theſe things by the Children of diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, who diſobey Chriſt, and walk contrary to his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine for ſelf and for ſelf-ends, though in words they may profeſs Chriſt, and ſay, they deſire to follow him: but all ſuch are ſhut out of the Scripture and Life of Chriſt, and condemned with the righteous Law, which was added be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of tranſgreſſion,
<note place="margin">Gal. 3.19.</note> which Chriſt came to fulfil, and not
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:168407:9"/>to deſtroy, and he that tranſgreſſeth any of the leaſt of his Commandements is guilty of all: and he that tranſgreſſeth and abideth not in the doctrine of Chriſt hath not God: and he that ſaith he loveth him,
<note place="margin">1 John 9.</note> and keepeth not his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, is a liar: and he that ſaith he abideth in Chriſt, ought alſo to walk as he walked: ſo with the Light all the world and its profeſſion is ſeen, and judged, and condemned: therefore all you, in whom there is any deſires after the living God, come out of the world to the true Light, wherewith you are enlightened, and profeſs nothing but what you live the life of, leaſt you be found in hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie, and with the hypocrites and diſſemblers you be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded in the fierceneſs of the wrath of God: Now you are warned, repent, and bring forth fruits meet for repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and amendment of light, for you all have a light from Chriſt, wherein if you believe and love it, and as it ariſes wait in it, and here you will know the way to life, and know your Teacher to be the Lord, who hath given you a light to guide your feet into the path of life, and reſt for your ſouls, and to know your Redeemer living, Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, and to deny the worlds Teachers and worſhips and profeſſion, which are all witneſſed againſt by Chriſt Jeſus,
<note place="margin">Mat. 25.30 Rom. 2.5, 6.</note> and by them whom he hath choſen out of the world, which light if you hate it, and love darkneſs better, it will be your condemnation from God, and from his knowledge, and from his Children, and Saints in Light, and utter dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs will be upon you, who go on in hatred againſt the Light, and there your torment and miſery will be exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing great, and you will know that God is clear when he Judges you, and executes his fierce wrath upon you, which the wicked cannot eſcape:</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>G. W.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:168407:10"/>
            <head>A Voyce of the Thunder of the Lord from his holy Temple, uttered forth to the Inhabitants of the Earth, who are in the Army of the Dragon, (whether Rulers, Teachers, or People.)</head>
            <p>O All ye Inhabitants of the Earth, high and low, rich and poor, great and ſmall, who lives without the fear of God in the fall, and take pleaſure in your unrighteouſneſs, and will not ſubmit your ſelves unto the Scepter of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, nor come under Chriſts government, but ſet your ſelves againſt the way of Righteouſneſs, in the enmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Dragon that old Serpent, and with the Beaſt, who hath his power and ſeat from the Dragon, ſets your ſelves to make war againſt the Lamb of God, and his elect; the terrible day of the Lord is proclaimed againſt you, a day of the Trumpet of the Lord, which is ſounding forth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you; a day of war and controverſie with you In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of the Earth, who live in careleſneſs and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneſs, who ſport your ſelves in the day time, you heady high minded ones, who live in pleaſure and riotouſneſs, who are in the pride of life, and exaltation, and heady high mindedneſs, who deſpiſe the Truth, and hate reproof, and will not be reformed of your evil wayes, but hates him that rebukes in the gate, and abhors him that ſpeaks
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:168407:10"/>uprightly, and perverts true judgment, and would not be judged for your wickedneſs, but rather chuſes to go on in the ſervitude of him who is your Captain and Leader in unrighteouſneſs, in hatred againſt the Truth, and the ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of it, to mock and reproach and deſpiſe them, and to perſecute the truth, and the ſervants of it, ſome in in ſlandering it, and backbiting the ſervants of it, and ſome in perſecuting and deſpitefully! uſing and impriſoning the Saints of the moſt high God, who witneſs forth his Name among the Children of men; you are all in the Army of the Dragon, and are fighting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain the Lamb, and ſtriving to ſuppreſs his Truth, that you might go on at eaſe in your wickedneſs.</p>
            <p>But though the Servants of the Lord ſuffer, and Chriſt be impriſoned and ſuffer as a Lamb among you for a time, through his long forbearance towards you, yet will he ariſe like a Lion, and avenge his quarrel upon you, and he will tear and devour the wicked, and overthrow the Dragon, and deſtroy all his off-ſpring, who are reſolved to make war againſt him, in Righteouſneſs will he make war, and in wiſdom will he plead his cauſe, and eaſe him of his enemies. Behold the day of his war and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie is begun already, and his hand will not ſpare, nor his eye pitty, nor his ſword return, till he hath accompliſhed his Decree, and overthrown his enemies, though he hath been ſlow to anger, and great in ſuffering for his Seed ſake, which he is gathering out of the world; yet now is his hand ſtretched out againſt <hi>Sions</hi> oppreſſors, and he will puniſh the world for their ſins, and will utterly over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw the Beaſt, and the falſe Prophet, and the conqueſt ſhall be his.</p>
            <p>Fear, fear and tremble, O all ye Inhabitants of the earth, who are at enmity againſt the pure God, for your Leader will fail you, and you will not be able to ſtand before the mighty God in his dreadful preſence; now is his Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders uttering, and his Trumpet a ſounding, and his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows are polliſhed, and his Sword is furbiſhed, and his
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:168407:11"/>Arm is ſtrong,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 7.13.</note> and his Wrath is waxing hot againſt the perſecutors, and his Hoſt is mighty, and Camp is very great, and his Day is exceeding terrible, who can abide it, all the Powers of the earth will not be able to ſtand in the day of his Battel,
<note place="margin">Jude 14,</note> he is coming with ten thouſand of his Saints to execute judgment upon the world, and to quit himſelf and his elect of all their Adverſaries, and utterly to overthrow their oppreſſors, though his elect and choſen and faithful ones endure great afflictions and long-ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<note place="margin">Luke 18.7.</note> yet their prayers is heard, and their cries is entered in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the eares of the Lord of Hoſts, who will not at all ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit the wicked, but will render his wrath with fury, and his rebukes with flames of fire. Wo, wo to all you that are ſet againſt him, behold his day cometh ſwiftly with wrath and fury, as a deſtruction from on high upon the ungodly: Now is his ſanctified ones called, and an enſign is lifted up to the Nations, and the day of vengeance is proclaimed, which haſteth greatly.</p>
            <p>Let all Nations fear and dread before the Lord of Hoſts; for they are all as potters veſſels before him, who will daſh them to pieces, and rule them with a rod of Iron, and he will have the uttermoſt parts of the earth for his poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 2.</note> and ſweep away all evil doers, and hew down all fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs trees, and bind the tares in bundels, and burn them, and there ſhall none be able to deliver from the power of the flame of his fiery indignation, which is kindled againſt the rebellious and crooked uncircumciſed generation.</p>
            <p>Conſider this all ye Inhabitants of the earth, high and low, great and ſmall, Rulers, and Teachers, and People, who perſecute the Innocent, and hate the Truth, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong whom many of the innocent Servants of the living God do ſuffer cruel uſage, and impriſonment, ſome have ſuffered till death in priſons for witneſſing forth the Truth and a good Conſcience, and many yet ſuffer in priſons and holes in this Nation, where their lives are ſought to be made
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:168407:11"/>a prey upon by Tyrants. O how will you anſwer theſe things before the dreadful God, who ſet your ſelves in the work of the Dragon, to war againſt the Lambs of Chriſts fold, and againſt Chriſt, for the Beaſt and his Kingdom behold inquiſition will the Lord make for the bloud of his Saints among the bloud-thirſty ones, who hate, perſecute and impriſon his dear Children, who are as dear unto him as the apple of his eye, who forgets not their ſufferings, who for his ſake loves not their lives unto death, who are counted as ſheep for the ſlaughter, and willingly bears the affliction and reproaches of Chriſt,
<note place="margin">Col. 1.24.</note> till his ſufferings be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled in their bodies, though it be to death and periſhing of the outward man,
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 5.13.</note> unto whom this day of the Lords wrath and controverſie, which is coming upon the wicked, will be a day of deliverance, a day of gladneſs, a day of joy and rejoycing for evermore; but a day of blackneſs,
<note place="margin">Mat. 5.10, 11.12.</note> and terror, and pain, and anguiſh to the oppreſſors of his Seed, who war for the Beaſt, and the falſe Prophet,
<note place="margin">Rev. 14.9, 10. Rev: 20.10.</note> who ſhall be caſt into the Lake which burneth, and there be tormented for ever and ever: here is the patience, and faith, and innocency of the Saints, who follow the Lamb whither ever he goeth, through ſufferings and tribulations, bleſſed are they that are not offended in him.</p>
            <p>Let all that follow him, and ſuffer for his Name, who are faithful through ſuffering, whatſoever they endure for his ſake, ſtand in his power, and might, and zeal, over all the powers of the earth, and over the wrath of the Dragon, and over the beaſt, though for a time he hath power to wear out the Saints of the moſt high,
<note place="margin">Dan. 7.25.</note> and think to change times and laws until a time, and times, and the dividing of time: But the Judgment ſhall ſit, and they ſhall take away his dominion, to conſume and deſtroy it unto the end, and the kingdom, and dominion, and the greatneſs of the kingdom, under the whole Heaven, ſhall be given to the people of the Saints of the moſt high, whoſe kingdom
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:168407:12"/>is an everlaſting Kingdom, and all Dominions ſhall ſerve and obey him.</p>
            <p>Let all the Saints and faithful ones be valiant and of good chear, whoſe travel and war is for the Lamb of God, who ſhall overcome all the powers of the Earth, and ſtand in his might and power and rejoyce for evermore, in him who is getting himſelf the dominion, whoſe right it is, for he is worthy to raign and rule, who is King of Kings, and Lord of Lords: Let all the powers of darkneſs fall before him, and greatneſs be aſcribed to his Name, who is King over all the Earth.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>G. W.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
